Guide to the Bayard Quincy Morgan Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Bayard Quincy Morgan papers
1907-1964
SC0863
Morgan, Bayard Quincy.
8 Linear feet
These papers include his translations of works by German authors into English with a few other translations; subject files which contain notes, articles, drafts of papers, lectures, exam questions, and a small amount of correspondence, 1922-51 and undated; course files, containing mostly notes, syllabi and reading lists, 1939-48 and undated; picture files consisting of printed illustrations of authors, historical figures, politicians, scientists, musicians, and others, undated; miscellaneous professional papers which include typescripts of papers and talks (some in German), a small amount of correspondence, and notebooks, 1920-42 and undated; and his reprints, 1907-1964.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Morgan earned his Ph.D. from the University of Leipzig in 1907. He taught at the University of Wisconsin from 1907 to 1934, when he joined the Stanford faculty as head of the German department. He focused on the field of translation and published a large number of translations of German literary works. He was appointed Professor Emeritus in 1948. He died in 1967.
Description of the Collection
These papers include his translations of works by German authors into English with a few other translations; subject files which contain notes, articles, drafts of papers, lectures, exam questions, and a small amount of correspondence, 1922-51 and undated; course files, containing mostly notes, syllabi and reading lists, 1939-48 and undated; picture files consisting of printed illustrations of authors, historical figures, politicians, scientists, musicians, and others, undated; miscellaneous professional papers which include typescripts of papers and talks (some in German), a small amount of correspondence, and notebooks, 1920-42 and undated; and his reprints, 1907-1964.
Access Terms
Morgan, Bayard Quincy.; German literature --Translations into English.; Translations.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Anzengruber, The Blot of Shame (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anzengruber; The Blot of Shame p.1-107 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anzengruber; The Blot of Shame p.108-31 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anzengruber; The Blot of Shame p.232-400 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anzengruber; The Blot of Shame p.401-531 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anzengruber; The God-Mastering Jakob (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Falckenberg; A Christmas Play (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fontane; Great Minoe (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Translations: French (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Translations: German (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Goering; Sea Fight (Correspondence Only, No Texts) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Gotthelf, The Black Spider (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Grillparzer, Hero and Leander (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Handel; Xerxes (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Harlan; The Nuremberg Egg (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Hauptmann; Florian Geyer (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hebbel; Agnes Bernauer (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hebbel; The Nibelungs, MSS Translation (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hebbel; The Nibelungs, p.1-159 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Hebbel; The Nibelungs, p.160-End (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Hebbel; The Nibelungs, p.1-159 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Hebbel; The Nibelungs, p.160-End (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Hebel; Two Sketches (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Hoffmann; Chevalier Chuck (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Hofmannsthal; Death and the Fool (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Holderin, Hyperion (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Holderin, Hyperion (copy 2) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Homer in English Hexameters (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Iliad; Misc.; [Fish] (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Iliad Book I (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Iliad Book II (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The Iliad Book III (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - The Iliad Book IV (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - The Iliad Book V (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The Iliad Book VI (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Keller; The Smith of His Own Fortune (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Lortzing, The Poacher (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Ludwig; “Between Heaven and Earth” (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Ludwig; “Between Heaven and Earth” (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Ludwig; “Between Heaven and Earth” (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Meyer, The Page of Gustavo Adolphus (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous items found with translations (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Mozart; Bastian and Bastienne (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Schnitzler, Literature, A Comedy in One Act (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Schnitzler, The Green Cockatoo (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Translations: Spanish (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Stifter, The Solar Eclipse of July 8, 1842 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Von Aue, The Story of Hapless Henry (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Wagner- The Poet of The Niblung’s Ring (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Wieland; Musarion (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Wieland; Musarion Book I (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Wieland; Principal Dates of Lessing’s Life (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Wieland; The Songbird/The Three Precepts (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Wieland; The Tub of Water (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Contemporary Literature: Class Materials (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Contemporary Literature: Notes (1) (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Contemporary Literature: Notes (2) (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Contemporary Literature: Notes (3) (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Contemporary Literature: Notes (4) (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Contemporary Literature: Notes (5) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Contemporary Literature: Notes (6) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Contemporary Literature: Notes (7) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - German Song: Characteristic Features of German Folksong (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - German Song: Das Deutsche Lied (1) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - German Song: Das Deutsche Lied (2) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - German Song: Folksong in German Life (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - German Song: Folksong Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - German Song: Notecards (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - German Folksongs (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - “Goethe’s Classicism” –MLA paper 1932 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Goethe: Faust- English- Part I (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Goethe: Faust II –notes, exam questions (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Goethe: Notecards (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Goethe: Notes, Sources, etc. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Goethe: Survey II, Lectures (in German) (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Goethe’s Verse: Correspondence and Mimeographed Lists (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Goethe’s Verse: Correspondence and Miscellaneous 1922-30 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Goethe’s Verse: Lang. and Lit. Club Article (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Goethe’s Verse: Miscellany (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Goethe’s Verse: Preface and Biographical Essay (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Goethe’s Verse Translations (1) (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Goethe’s Verse Translations (2) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Goethe’s Verse Translations (3) (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Goethe’s Verse: Versions by Other Hands (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Lecture: American Negro Folksong (notes) (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Lecture: Beethoven’s Chamber Music, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Lecture: Brahms, April 1933 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Lecture: Dasdeutsche Kinderlied, July 1933 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Lecture: Der Amerikafahrer Und Sein Problem (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Lecture: der Deutsche Wald (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Lecture: Faust (in German), N.d. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Lecture: Fruhlins in deutschenlied, WHA, May 1933 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Lecture: German Folksongs (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Lecture: German Folk Tales (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Lecture Notes: on Germany, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Lecture: Humor im Lied, June 1933 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Lectures, Misc., 1933-38 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Lectures, Misc., 1939-44 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Lecture Notes, Misc., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Lecture: Misc. Papers (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Lecture on Nazi Education (notes) (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Lecture: Numbers in the Nibelungenlied, Berkeley Nov. 1934 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Lecture: Peaceful Warfare, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Lecture: Richard Strauss, May 1934 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Lecture: Uber die Zablen in Nibelungenlied (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Lecture: [Various Composers] (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Literature: A-D (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Literature: A-G un-filed (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Literature: Alexis (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Literature: Anzengruber (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Literature: Auerbach (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Literature: Bohlau (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Literature: Brod (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Literature: Doblin (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Literature: E-G (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Literature: Ebner- Eschenbach (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Literature: Fontane (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Literature: Frenssen (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Literature: Freytag (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Literature: German Lit. (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Literature: Gotthelf (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Literature: Grillparzer (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Literature: Grimm (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Literature: Gutzkow (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Literature: H-I (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Literature: H-M (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Literature: Hauptmann (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Literature: Hebbel (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Literature: Heine (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Literature: Heyse (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Literature: Huch (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Literature: Immermann (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Literature: J-K (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Literature: Kafka (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Literature: Kaiser (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Literature: Keller, G (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Literature: Keyserling (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Literature: Kleist (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Literature: Kolbenheyer (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Literature: L-M (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Literature: Lucka (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - Literature: Ludwig, O. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Literature: Mann, H. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Literature: Mann, Th. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Literature: Meyer, C.F. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Literature: N-R (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Literature: Nietzsche (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Literature: Polenz (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Literature: Raabe (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Literature: Reuter (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Literature: Ritcher (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Literature: Rosegger (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Literature: S (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Literature: Schnitzler (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Literature: Schopenhauer (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Literature: Sealsfield (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Literature: Seidel (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Literature: Spielhagen (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Literature: Stehr (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Literature: Stifter (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Literature: Storm (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Literature: Sudermann (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Literature: T-Z (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Literature: Tieck (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Literature: Toller (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Literature: Viebig (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Literature: Wagner (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Literature: Wassenmann (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Literature: Werfel (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Literature: Zahn (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Literature; Zweig (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Misc. Notes: The American Secondary School, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Misc. Notes: Barock (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Misc. Notes: Form and Substance in German Literature (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Misc. Notes: General (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Misc. Notes: German Classics (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Misc. Notes: German Teachers in America (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - Misc. Notes: Goethe and Faust (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - Misc. Notes: Goethe Today (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Misc. Notes: Lyrik (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Misc. Notes: The Melody of the English Question, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Misc. Notes: Modern Lit., 1941 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Misc. Notes: The Novel (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Misc. Notes: Novel-France (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Misc. Notes: Rhythm and Metre (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Survey I & II: Notes (1) (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Survey I & II: Notes (2) (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Survey I & II: Notes (3) (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Survey I & II: Notes (4) (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Survey I & II: Notes (5) (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Survey I & II: Notes (6) (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Survey I & II: Notes (7) (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Survey I & II: Notes (8) (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Survey I & II: Notes (9) (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Survey I & II: Notes on Wieland, C.M. (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - A50 (German Poetry) Course file (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - C102 German Lit. 1600-1800 course file, 1939-48 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - C102 – BQM Notes (1) (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - C102 – BQM Notes (2) (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - C102 – BQM Notes (3) (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - C102 – BQM Notes (4) - Lessing (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - C102 – BQM Notes (5) (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Pictures: A- Azorin (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Pictures: Bac- Bla (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Pictures: Blo-Byron (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Pictures: Cab-Car (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Pictures: Cas- Cler (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Pictures: Clev- Cuv (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Pictures: D (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Pictures: E-F (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Pictures: G (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Pictures: H-I (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Pictures: J-K (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Pictures: L (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Pictures: Ma- Me (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Pictures: Mi-O (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Pictures: P (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Pictures: R (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Pictures: Sack-Sou (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Pictures: Spa- Swin (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Pictures: Ta- Tw (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Pictures: Uhl- Urb (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Pictures: Valle- Virg (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Pictures: Wallace- Woo (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Pictures: Y (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Pictures: Z (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - BQM, Alltag in U.S.A (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Morgan- Castilleja School –Vespers- (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - The Changing Complexion of German Literature (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence Received 1935 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence- Homer 1911-16 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Morgan- Das Volkslied Der Nord Amerikani Schen Neger (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Das Volkslied im Deutschen Leben (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - The Dial- Homer (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Die Stimme des Auslands (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - “Divine Predestination and Humor Freedom of Will” (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Education in Germany 1945 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Morgan – Ein Einblick in das Alltagsleben einer Nordamerikanischen Kleinstadt (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Einfuhrung in Das Afro- Amerikan Sche Volkslied (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Festredezum “ Deutschen Tag” 1937 (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Historical [re need for language instruction], San Francisco, Fall 1942 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Holzapfel (1) (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Holzapfel (2) (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Letters Received Re-Pubs (Box 14, Folder 25)
  - Notebook 1928 (Box 14, Folder 26)
  - Notebook- Text for tour of Cologne (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Cards from notebook on tour of Cologne (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - “On the Use of Numbers in the Nibelungenlied” (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Schwarz und Weiss in U.S.A. (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Morgan- Notes On the Translating of Comedy, Stanford Radio Hour, May 10, 1937 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Typescript “ On the 20th Lenz Crossed the Mountains.” (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - United States and the Coming of Peace (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - “Verses to Commemorate the First Quarter Century of Alpha Chi Ro” 1920 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Versuch Einer Analyse des Afro-Amerikanische Volksliedes (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Zur Schlussfeier derDeutschen Schule (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Reprints, 1907-July 1917 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Reprints, 1923-29 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Reprints, 1930-35 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Reprints, 1936-39 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Reprints, 1940-Feb. 1943 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Reprints, Nov. 1943 - 1948 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Reprints, 1950-Summer 1954 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Reprints, 1954-64 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Reprints, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Additional material, Accession ARCH-2010-018
  - Files of correspondence, galleys, and typescripts for various translations 1950s-60s (Box 17)
  - Files on the German novel (Box 17)
  - Wallenstein typescript [more Wallenstein in box 17] (Box 18)
  - Typescript for his “Critical Bibliography of German Literature in English Translation” (Box 18)
  - File on German Lit – pictures [printed illustrations] (Box 18)
  - File: Karl Reuning [typescript of his lecture and correspondence with Morgan, 1940] (Box 18)
  - File: 19th century novel (Box 18)
  - File: Grammar, notes and queries (Box 18)
  - File: miscellaneous (possibly class materials) (Box 18)
  - Morgan’s reprints (Box 18)
  - Books: A. E. Brinckmann’s Europäische Humanitas, Dürer bis Goya, 1950; and Taschenatlas fur Eisenbahnreisende, 1927 (Box 18)